# Nasr Kasrin (PhD)

96050 Bamberg, Germany



## Summary .

Versatile software architect and product strategist with a history of guiding successful projects spanning various domains (including data architecture, social networks, mobile apps, games, robotics, and Al), team sizes ranging from 2 to 10 members, and diverse settings, from agile B2C environments to R&D projects backed by €3.5 million in public funding.

With expertise at the intersection of engineering and product leadership, I excel in delivering cutting-edge solutions that drive business growth and enhance user experiences (See n42r.github.io for more).

# **Projects**

Muze Al

**OPEN SOURCE SOFTWARE** 

github.com/n42r/muze-ai

Conceptualized and developed an early AI/LLM music discovery tool, bypassing the reliance on Spotify's music recommendation metadata.

Guestrrday

**OPEN SOURCE SOFTWARE** 

github.com/n42r/guestrrday

· Engineered an open-source music tagging tool capable of processing over 20,000 items, enhancing music organization and accessibility.

### The Basin Network (Doctoral Project)

ARCHITECTURAL MODEL

n42r.github.io/phd

- Conceived and implemented a novel architectural pattern for data cataloging, improving on data mesh and data space models in 3 repects: precision, level of detail, and generalization, culminating in the award of a PhD with distinction.
- Published findings in 2 journals, contributing to advancements in the field of data management.

**SIMUTOOL Data Lake** 

SAAS (EUROPEAN UNION PUBLICLY FUNDED PROJECT)

github.com/simutool

- Built a data lake SaaS for a consortium of 8 manufacturing companies, cutting turnover time by 30% by fostering data-driven cooperation.
- · Architected the application, developed the back-end, and led an agile team to develop various value-added clients which led to a 90% user satisfaction and the success of the project based on the evaluation of the EU committee of experts.

**Greetings Studio** 2012 - 2014

SOCIAL NETWORK/IOS MOBILE APP (B2C)

n42r.github.io/gs

- · Directed the agile development of a social network and Apple iOS mobile app facilitating the creation and sharing of E-cards and images, optimizing user engagement leading to 10-fold growth in user base.
- Architected the for scalability and maintainability, leading to a reduction of 40% of extra development that was originally spent circumventing technical architecture debt.

Tawla (Backgammon)

GAME/IOS MOBILE APP (B2C)

n42r.github.io/tw

- Elevated app ratings from 3 to 4.5/5 stars by the implementation of advanced AI players, enhancing gameplay dynamics.
- Achieved a 10% increase in positive reviews due to devising and implementing a sophisticated random number generator for the dice algorithm, which resulted in more enjoyable gameplay.

ArtSapiens 2D Soccer

AI/ROBOTICS SOFTWARE TO COMPETE IN THE 2011 INTERNATIONAL ROBOCUP COMPETITION

ssim.robocup.org

· Co-founded and co-led a team of 10 in developing robotics/Al software to compete in the International RoboCup Competition, which qualifications and earned a spot in 2011 competition in Kuala Lumpur, Malaysia.

# **Work Experience**

#### Research Associate (Architect | Team Lead)

2015 - 2020

University of Bamberg (Third-party Funded Project)

Bamberg, Germany

- Directed a 4-year project to develop a data management SaaS for a €3.5 million 8-company EU manufacturing project, optimizing data discovery, collaboration, and turnaround time, and resulting in enhanced operational efficiency (See qithub.com/simutool for more).
- Cultivated close relationships with 10+ external partners, facilitating deep domain understanding and precise requirements identification.
- Engineered a read-heavy, horizontally scalable SaaS, ensuring seamless operations and future-proof architecture (ex., stateless nodes).

#### Team Leader | Software Architect | R&D Engineer

2011 - 2014

TayaIT

Cairo, Egypt

- Directed agile technical teams, ranging from 2 to 5 members, in the development of two enduring social media/mobile products, driving perpetual augmentation of app rankings (4.5 starts) and a 10-fold increase in user engagement (See 'Greetings Studio' and 'Tawla' in Projects).
- Reduced feedback-development cycle times by 25% by coordinating cross-functional collaboration between technical, business, and UI/UX teams, streamlining workflows and fostering tighter cooperation and heightened productivity.
- Saved the company over 10-man months by investigating emerging technologies and alternative project paths and advising the CEO in adopting better paths or avoiding dead-ends and sub-optimum paths.

## Skills\_

**DEVELOPMENT**Python, Docker (multi-container), Linux CLI, git, and low-/no-code (bubble.io). Formerly, C++, Lisp, Java.**DATABASES**MongoDB, Neo4j, SQL, Google Firebase, and Resource Description Framework (RDF) / Semantic Data.

**LEADERSHIP** Empathetic leadership and coaching, agile/lean project leadership, change management.

ARCHITECTURE
Distributed architectures, modular monoliths (clean/hexagonal architecture), HTTP API interface design.

Domain EXPERTISE
Data integration, governance, interoperability, standardization, cataloguing, domain modeling, robotics/AI.

Critical and conceptual thinking, collaboration/teamwork, clear communication of complex concepts.

## **Education**

#### Otto-Friedrich-Universität Bamberg

2020 - 2023

PhD. (Dr. rer. nat.), Faculty of Information Systems & Applied Computer Science

Bamberg, Germany

## The German University in Cairo

2009 - 2010

MSc. (Masters of Science), Faculty of Computer Science & Engineering

Cairo, Egypt

#### The German University in Cairo

2003 - 2008

BSc. (Bachelors of Science), Faculty of Computer Science & Engineering

Cairo, Egypt

# **Publications**

Full list available at: scholar.google.com/citations?user=JgS4-1cAAAAJ

# Languages

ENGLISH Fluent
ARABIC Fluent

**GERMAN** B1 Telc Certified (Good Understanding, Basic Speaking)